so what is the purpose the rules
precepts why do you why do you practice
renunciation the purpose of it is
developing the strength of your mind and
the absolutely first step for that is to
be able to say no to yourself to say no
to your desires wins habits so every all
of the main rules upon which our
practice is based is they're very
practical so to speak functional
necessary in that sense they're not held
because of a belief or because of the
authority their help because they hold
in themselves the practice of meditation
and development of the mind to basically
think of the rules as a fertile ground
where you can plant seeds of a plant or
some trees so it has it's not it's not a
tree it's not that it's not the seed but
having a grown tree would be impossible
if you don't have a fertile fertile
ground to do so so in that sense you see
the necessity of the fertile ground you
see the necessity of the rules without
them there's no point if you cultivating
seeds and watering the plant when you
have destroyed the fertility of the
ground when you have compromised the
fundamental rules sorry
well you're trying to grow the the
freedom freedom of the mind because the
mind is bound by the desire by the
craving by the feelings mind is liable
to feelings which means when suffering
arises you won't be able to prevent it
when pleasure arises you won't be able
but to indulge it means you're
controlled by what you feel and you are
controlled because the mind is too weak
in regard to what it feels so you want
to become stronger than all those things
and the first step to developing of that
strength is
me restraint being able to say no not to
everything forever but the certain
things that are inseparable from desire
craving ill-will hate anything
unwholesome recipe yeah eating at a
certain time it's again it's just like
you you eat because it is necessary for
the body to remain alive but you don't
want to be using the sensuality as a
form of escape and then you just keep
eating throughout a day eating only what
you like and so on so you're recognized
a degree of necessarily to eat and
that's what you focus on and yeah if you
eat enough calories once in the day
that's absolutely fun discipline no
reason to eat more eating more inches
well you need is gonna is gonna ban -
it's gonna be bound to come out of
sensuality out of craving out of desire
but it's not a life-threatening hunger
so basically in the evening you have
desire to eat and instead of habitually
just giving in to desire and satisfying
it by any means you you you force
yourself to reflect on it because you
know you won't eat you won't break the
rule so as a form of restraint what's
the alternative
well it's to think okay why how why am i
pulled by this design why this hunger
controlling my mind and that's how you
that's how you go beyond the design
eventually know you want you you'd be
free from hunger but the hunger was not
your desire yeah there would have been
no desire without the hunger but the
hunger is not a desire desire is always
mental so when the hunger and the
physical state effect control your mind
then it becomes a desire which means you
might go and remove the
sickle state but the liability of your
mind to be controlled by the physical
states remains which means next physical
thing comes and you're going to equally
be bound by the same desire hence you
don't send you can't set this for a
desire and everybody knows that you can
be chasing and engaging in all sorts of
sensuality you can have a satisfied
desire what cuz it's not there when
you're trying to set it right
you're satisfying physical circumstances
but those are nobody desire it yeah
desire is inseparable from those but
it's not those it's not those things so
the precepts are basically just like
laying out to the ground where you can
practice just putting up a fence
fertilizing the ground and agreeing upon
those things as a starting point you
have to start somewhere so all the
precepts were basically that's women
they were quite functional in that sense
you eat in the beginning the monks were
allowed to eat in the evening it was not
specified to be done in the morning they
could eat many times a day
but then you were sort of becoming
impractical for various reasons going
out at night to collect the food getting
out go up so all sorts of accidents and
so on so and so then he was sort of a
rule was brought in you eat it you eat
it at the right time so you don't go out
to collect food at night you go during
the day then they could still eat at
night but then you stop eating at night
as well you just eat when you go and get
the food you just becomes more practical
easier and you don't spend the rest of
the day being concerned and planning
about the food you spend it practicing
restraint and practicing wisdom and
practicing meditation
well those yeah the eight precepts those
are the basis of practice those are
that's what defines their fertile ground
they're not negotiable like how can you
possibly be practising the clarity of
the mind developing the strength of in
mind when you're drinking alcohol that
clearly directly affecting the clarity
of the mind and it has no practical
value like you need to eat
some food you need to meet the certain
degree of a certain amount of calories
you don't need to drink alcohol hence
it's always going to be central reasons
and even people say oh I drink only
because people around me pressure me to
do so that's also central reason you're
basically afraid of affecting adversely
the central environment around you you
don't upset anyone you don't have to
have to be kind of ostracized or
whatever by a friend so you drink that's
ridiculous you're trying to develop the
strength of your mind yet you're giving
to the basic weaknesses like oh they're
laughing and they're teasing me so what
how can you be beyond suffering beyond
the favorite emotion with so much mere
teasing is affecting you and you can't
be comment on your behavior
but this precept salons all you have to
do know of course that it's a photo not
you can have all the further ground you
want if you don't have the actual well
cultivated seeds and if you don't put
the work in maintaining that soil today
not gonna grow because you have to water
it you have to provide enough some you
have to work around it once you plant
the seed but just just leaving just
hoping for the for the soul to do it's
only want to do it to do the work you
want yeah you need to have the rules
that cover the necessary basis and those
are basically what is known as a preset
or 10 precept if you wanna take for
maybe a step further but that's it
everything else is derived from that
basis it cannot add more to it so in
that sense yeah having 3,000 rules it's
not necessarily if you have covered the
basis of these 8 pieces if you don't do
anything unwholesome on the account of
the eight precepts that's it
you have you have sufficient basis for
complete freedom from suffering from
feelings and everything else
don't establish themselves in the fridge
right don't kill don't steal don't cheat
or preferably or ideally be a completely
celibate we believe we'll live a
completely celibate lifestyle don't well
don't
sorry drink yeah don't drink and take
drugs in the sense of don't consume
things that directly affect mindfulness
and awareness and composure so you have
to those are like the five basic ones
and they have to be basically taken
seriously and I'm talking about somebody
who still lives in the world but for a
monk then you have the eight pieces you
have the non non beautification non
indulgence and sleep and not eating at
the wrong times as in not just spend the
whole day eating around and thinking
about food so you want to start kind of
harnessing your mind basically
harnessing the out pours the behaviors
of your mind that are founded upon
desire and non restraint so basically
you're setting up a fence tying it down
pinning it down until it calms down
that's what the presets are but in
itself they're not it's not enough
they're necessary basis the container
but then the work needs to be done
within that once you fence the yard off
for the wild horse you need to start
training yeah the first you can't start training
yeah the first you can't start training
it inconceivable when you can always run
off into the mountains but now you
fenced it off completely you repaired
any any patches that he was escaping
through you brought it back now he can't
escape you wait for it to calm down
because he will come down sooner or
later he's gonna get tired running
around in circles when it's calm then
you start training it but then if you
remove the fence and you haven't trained
it it's going to
on off again so you have to keep the
fence until it's fully trained and when
it's fully trained then it doesn't
matter the fence stays and that's
basically the definition of the pieces
Suman is a lay person the five preset
are at a certain degree of that of that
fence which is which is a good thing
because you are taming down the wild
horse which what mind is really for most
people so you'll be taking a bit more
control over your own behavior of your
own desires over their own sort of
impulses that usually you can't say no
to
yeah that's the first step